Guide to the North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company Archives, 1850, 1888-2000s and undated, bulk 1920-2008 RL.00936
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Photographic Materials, 1888-2008 and undated; 24 boxes
  - Photographic Prints, 1888-2008 and undated
    - Historic Images, circa 1885-1952 and undated
      - Home office clerks, 1909, 1 print (Box 184)
      - Mrs. C.S. Moore; Booker and Charles Spaulding, Jr., circa 1910, 2 prints (Box 184)
      - Merrick residence, circa 1910, 2 prints (Box 184)
      - Booker T. Washington visit, 1910, 3 prints (Box 184)
      - Office images, circa 1910-1940, 8 prints (Box 184)
      - A.M. Moore, 1919-1923, 4 prints (Box 184)
      - C.C. Spaulding, circa 1920-1952, 2 folders; 49 prints (Box 184)
        Folders house a mix of black-and-white mounted and unmounted true photographic prints, as well as printed images on paper, also black-and-white. Included are portraits of Spaulding as well as several images of office settings from the 1920s through his presidency. Accompanying the Spaulding images are a few photographs of others, inscribed to Spaulding.
      - Meetings, circa 1920-1940, 7 prints (Box 122)
      - People, circa 1920-1950, 37 prints (Box 122)
      - Glee Club, Quintet, circa 1929, and 1991 sheet music for Dreams, 4 photographs; 1 piece of sheet music (Box 122)
      - Merrick family, circa 1930-1960, 10 prints (Box 122)
      - William Kennedy, Jr., circa 1930, 2 prints (Box 122)
      - Thrift Clubs, circa 1933-1941, 19 prints (Box 122)
      - Tennis championship, 1938 Sept. 3, 1 print (Box 122)
      - Mrs. E.H. Berry and daughter, 1939-1944, 10 prints (Box 122)
      - Model of office, circa 1930, 1 print (Box 122)
      - Payment of first claim in Atlanta office, circa 1940, 1 print (Box 122)
      - Master contract delivery, 1945 Mar., 1 print (Box 122)
      - Basketball team, undated, 1 print (Box 122)
      - Historic images photograph album assembled by NCM staff, 1920s-1960s (Box 122-A)
        Collection of 132 black-and-white photographs ranging in size from approx. 3x4" to 8x10", with three predominant types of images appearing in this order: the exterior of the home office on Parrish Street in Durham; interiors from the 1920s-1940s, including many early departments and their staff and equipment; and portraits of officers and other staff. Many of the subjects are identified on the back of the print. A series of commercially-made images of the medical and other departments in the 1940s are particularly of note. A few image slots are empty (#16, 134-137).
    - Public Relations Image Files, 1942-2008
      Arranged in loose chronological order, this subseries contains mixed images, almost all black-and-white, of events, people, and places produced by the Public Relations Department for exhibits and publications such as The Whetstone and The Pilot.
      Some folders are related to specific issues of publications or composite pages while others are more intermixed. Many of the images in this subseries overlap with other subseries. Those depicted include NCM officers, employees, their families, policy holders, politicians, and prominent figures such as Robert F. Kennedy, Martin Luther King, Jr., and Jesse Jackson. Some negatives, reprints of older images, clippings, and related paper materials are also included. The bulk of the material dates from the 1960s.
      - PR, 1942-1987, 4 folders; 125 prints (Box 122)
      - PR, 1950-1970, 4 of 5 folders; 165 prints (Box 122)
      - PR, 1950-1970, 1 of 5 folders; 35 prints (Box 123)
      - PR, 1950-1990, 2 folders; 31 prints (Box 123)
      - PR, 1950-2000, 15 prints (Box 123)
      - PR, 1960-1970, 14 of 25 folders; 362 prints (Box 123)
      - PR, 1960-1970, 11 of 25 folders; 290 prints (Box 124)
      - The Pilot materials, 1960-1980, 3 folders; 143 prints (Box 124)
      - PR, 1960-1980, 6 folders; 111 prints (Box 124)
      - PR, 1970-1980, 7 folders; 190 prints (Box 125)
      - PR, 1970-1990, 4 folders; 81 prints (Box 125)
      - PR, 1980-1990, 6 of 12 folders; 219 prints (Box 125)
      - PR, 1980-1990, 6 of 12 folders; 123 prints (Box 126)
      - PR, 1980-2000, 10 folders; 483 prints (Box 126)
      - PR, 1980-2008, 25 prints (Box 126)
      - PR, 1990-2000, 3 folders; 81 prints (Box 126)
      - Collins scrapbook, 1992-1995, 21 prints (Box 127)
      - Exhibit photographs, 6 folders; 183 prints (Box 127)
        Contains reprints of photographs and drawings from different periods in NCM history, compiled for exhibits in the 1980-2000 period.
      - Exhibit photos from NIA Convention, 2003, 11 prints (Box 127)
      - Proof pages with portraits of employees for unidentified publication, 1970s; 2 folders (Box OV57)
    - People, 1910-2008
      Files were assembled by NCM staff, and arranged into employees, officers, and other people sub-groupings. Other images of people are found scattered throughout the collection, but are particularly concentrated in all of the other sub-groups of the Photographic Materials Series, and in the Printed Materials Series.
      - Employees, 1910-2008
        Contains portraits and group photographs of NCM employees from the home office and various district offices. In addition to headshots, employees are shown working and attending various events. Arranged by location, when possible.
        - Baltimore district, 1940-1962, 36 prints (Box 127)
        - Birmingham district, 1940-1970, 51 prints (Box 127)
        - Chicago district, 1950-1970, 19 prints (Box 128)
        - Georgia district, circa 1910-1980, 3 folders; 115 prints (Box 128)
        - Group shots of employees from various districts, 1961-1968 and undated, 8 prints (Box 128)
        - Los Angeles district, circa 1960, 25 prints (Box 128)
        - Newark district, 1950-1970, 63 prints (Box 128)
        - Norfolk district, 1993, 1 print (Box 128)
        - North Carolina district, circa 1930-2000, 5 folders; 246 prints (Box 128)
        - Pennsylvania district, 1940-1980, 109 prints (Box 128)
        - South Carolina district, circa 1920-1980, 90 prints (Box 128)
        - Tennessee district, 1930-1980, 2 folders; 117 prints (Box 128)
        - Washington DC district, 1930-1965, 54 prints (Box 129)
        - Women, 1926-2008, 7 folders; 106 prints (Box 129)
        - Other employees, 1940-2000, 8 folders; 422 prints (Box 129)
        - Other employees, 1975-2008, 1 of 8 folders; 13 prints (Box 129)
        - Other employees, 1975-2008, 7 of 8 folders; 300 prints (Box 130)
        - Other employees, 1989-2004 and undated; 4 folders (Box 186)
      - Officers, 1910-2008
        Contains portraits and group photographs of NCM presidents, officers, Board of Directors, and Executive Committee. Images of officers' family members are also included. Contains formal portraits, group photographs, and snapshots taken at various events. Arranged in loose chronological order.
        - Merrick, Kennedy Jr., Kennedy III, and Sloan headshots, 1910-1990, 8 prints (Box 130)
        - Board of Directors, 1929-1995, 4 folders; 69 prints (Box 130)
        - C.C. Spaulding, circa 1940-1952, 14 prints (Box 130)
        - C.C. Spaulding, Cox, and Merrick visit to Atlanta, 1934, 1 print (Box 130)
        - J.L. Wheeler, 1943-1957, 9 prints (Box 130)
        - W.A. Clement, 1950-1998, 2 folders; 79 prints (Box 130)
        - Joseph W. Goodloe, 1952-1972, 2 folders; 75 prints (Box 130)
        - Officers at various events, 1955-1978, 2 of 5 folders; 82 prints (Box 130)
        - Unidentified male executive with glasses and Shriners' lapel pin, probably 1950s (Box 130)
        - W. A. Clement and Asa Spaulding, circa 1960, 3 photo albums (Box 131)
        - Officers at various events, 1955-1978, 3 of 5 folders; 109 prints (Box 132)
        - Asa T. Spaulding, 1956-1968, 2 folders; 68 prints (Box 132)
        - William J. Kennedy, III, circa 1970s-1986, 2 folders; 14 prints (Box 132)
        - Executive Committee, 1987-1988, 10 prints (Box 132)
        - Bert Collins, 1987-1996, 2 folders; 30 prints (Box 132)
        - William J. Kennedy, III and Bert Collins, circa 1990, 60 prints (Box 132)
        - James Speed, 2004-2008, 27 prints (Box 132)
      - Other People, 1930-2008
        Contains various portraits and group photographs of employees, family members, policy holders, executives from other insurance companies, scholarship recipients, and HBCU administrators. Many are currently unidentified. Arranged in loose chronological order.
        - Policy holders, 1930-1970, 141 prints (Box 132)
        - University and high school students, 1935-1965, 76 prints (Box 132)
        - Merrick and Moore Scholars, 1938-1970, 73 prints (Box 132)
        - Group shots, 1940-1965, 24 prints (Box 132)
        - Military service, circa 1945-1970, 10 prints (Box 133)
        - Employees, policy holders, and other people, 1945-1990, 4 folders; 220 prints (Box 133)
        - HBCU administrators, 1950-1970, 22 prints (Box 133)
        - People, 1980-2008, 7 folders; 176 prints (Box 133)
    - Places, 1905-2008
      Primarily contains images of the North Carolina Mutual physical plant, including different office buildings, men and women staff members on the job, workspaces, equipment, mainframes, decorations for specific events, and the construction of the 1965 home office. Includes photographic images of the original office buildings from circa 1900 to an architect's rendering of the new home office, circa 1963. Other images of the home offices can be found in oversize photo boxes and in the exhibits series. Of particular interest are a series of images of NCM employees' homes, which are labelled with the employee's name, rank, and city. Also included are scenes in Durham, N.C. and snapshots from business trips to Puerto Rico and Miami.
      - Employees' homes, 1930-1960, 52 prints (Box 133)
      - NCM home office, front of frame building, circa 1900 (exhibit reproduction) (Box 133)
      - NCM Building, aerial view, ca. 1966 (reproduction), box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV23)
      - Physical plant and office scenes, and home office buildings, 1905-2008, 9 folders; 154 prints (Box 133)
      - Hurricane Hugo damage, 1989, 16 prints (Box 134)
      - Business trip snapshots, circa 1988-1995, 46 prints (Box 134)
      - List of digital images of a variety of locations, 2007 (Box 134)
    - Oversized Prints
      Includes photographic prints and photograph albums, arranged in original order as received, with mixed contents in boxes and folders. The great majority are black-and-white, with many featuring professional portraits of NC Mutual leaders and officers. The majority of the 20 panoramic photographs feature large group portraits taken at national and regional insurance association conventions and meetings, some as early as 1916 and 1917, and range in size from 18.75x8 inches to 44.5x8 inches. One panoramic photo at an unknown location features well-known educators including John Hope, Julius Rosenwald, Mary McLeod Bethune, and others.
      - Robert F. Kennedy at NIA convention photograph album, 1962, box size: 11x14 inches (Box OV27)
      - Meeting album, 1985, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV28)
      - Marketing mid-year conference album, 1993, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV28)
      - NCM events album, 1994, box size: 11x17 inches (Box OV29)
      - NCM annual policyholders meeting, circa 2004, box size: 11x17 inches (Box OV29)
      - John Merrick, black-and-white portrait in paper frame, circa 1917, box size: 11x14 inches (Box OV30)
      - "Sons and a daughter of some of the Mgrs. of the N.C. Mut. Life Ins. Co.," group portrait taken outdoors, 1939 April, box size: 11x14 inches (Box OV30)
        Last names written on photo include: Harvey, Clement, Leathers-Babcock (the daughter), Harrods or Hassouds, Alston, Bolden, Leathers. There are several Harveys, Clements, and Boldens.
      - Unidentified man, photographic portrait, circa 1910s, box size: 11x14 inches (Box OV30)
      - Mrs. Martha Merrick Donnell and party at launching of S.S. John Merrick, July 11, 1943 (printed clipping of image), box size: 11x14 inches (Box OV30)
      - C.C. Spaulding, cut-out of head shot, mounted, undated, box size: 11x14 inches (Box OV30)
      - William Kennedy, cut-out of head shot, mounted, undated, box size: 11x14 inches (Box OV30)
      - Staff of Augusta, Georgia home office, group portrait taken in front of building, 1934, box size: 11x14 inches (Box OV30)
      - They were at the cabin now..., engraving of African American couple in front of a cabin, artist Allen C. Redwood, engraver E.H. Wellington, 1886 (modern black-and-white photographic reproduction), box size: 11x14 inches (Box OV30)
        Originally an illustration for a short story by Thomas Nelson Page, Ole 'Stracted, published in Harper's Magazine, Oct. 1886.
      - Composite of engraved vignettes from the first N.C. Colored Industrial Association fair, held in Raleigh, artist Joseph Becker, 1879 (modern black-and-white photographic reproduction), box size: 11x14 inches (Box OV30)
        Scenes include exhibitors arriving at the fair with livestock, ox-drawn wagons, Gov. Jarvis giving a speech, and men, women, and children on the grounds and in the hall.
      - NCM home office, Parrish St., Durham, NC, after 1921, box size: 11x14 inches; 2 copies (Box OV30)
      - View of downtown Durham, N.C., with NCM home office and Hill Building, after 1937, box size: 11x14 inches (Box OV30)
      - NCM 60th anniversary banquet, shot of all seated guests in hall, mounted, 1958, box size: 11x14 inches (Box OV30)
      - Unidentified woman, photographic portrait, 1930s?, box size: 11x14 inches (Box OV30)
      - Historic images, mixed, 5 folders; box size: 12x18 inches (Box OV31)
        Some of the materials in this box are fragile and in need of preservation. Please contact Research Services to use this material, as contents should be photocopied before being handled.
      - Events, people, places, 7 folders; box size: 12x18 inches (Box OV32)
      - Historic images, people, places, box size: 16x20 inches; 7 folders (Box OV33)
      - Historic images, events, 8 folders; box size: 24x30 inches (Box OV34)
      - Historic images, events, 1 folder; box size: 21x25 inches (Box OV38)
      - NCM District Managers' meeting, circa 1940s; 60th anniversary banquet, 1958, box size: 23x31 inches (Box OV45)
      - Panels used for exhibits or internal communications, 1968-1988, Panels are roughly 36 inches tall and 16 inches wide.; 4 items (Oversize-folder 1)
        Panels include listings of "Our current Fortune 500 clients" and "Our current public sector clients," a 1968 panel with a few photographic images of real estate investments, and data on assets, insurance in force, and policy holders, and a panel cutout of the new office on Chapel Hill Street, Durham, N.C.
      - "Committed to African American wealth building since 1898," color advertising panels, "draft," 2000s, Panels measure roughly 24x36 inches.; 4 items (Oversize-folder 2)
        Each panel contains a large color photographic portrait of African American family members with children, and each has "draft" written in top corner. Two of the images are the same as panels in Oversize Folder 3.
      - "Committed to African American wealth building since 1898," color advertising panels, 2000s, Panels measure roughly 24x36 inches.; 3 items (Oversize-folder 3)
        Panels feature large color photographic portraits of African American family members: one with a man and a child, and one with a woman and a child. These images are the same as two draft panels in Oversize Folder 3. The third panel is a duplicate image.
      - "Platinum Plus Whole Life Plan," color poster with African American family, 2000s, Panels measure roughly 24x36 inches. (Oversize-folder 3)
        Advertisement poster features a large color photographic portrait of African American family with man, woman, and one child.
      - "Raise your financial IQ: your guide to financial literacy," North Carolina Mutual, Durham, N.C. office, color calendar of events poster, 2006, Poster measures approximately 24x36 inches. (Oversize-folder 4)
      - Unidentified [insurance agents'?] meeting, panoramic photograph taken on a beach, circa early 1920s (Oversize-folder 5)
      - Annual convention of the N.C. Association of Insurance Agents, Asheville, N.C., 1917 July 12, panoramic photograph (Oversize-folder 5)
      - Mid-year conference, National Association of Insurance Agents, Mt. Vernon, Virginia, 1917 February 16, panoramic photograph (Oversize-folder 5)
        Includes several women in the front row.
      - National Association of Insurance Agents, Signal Mountain, Chattanooga, Tennessee, 1922 March 14, 15, 16, panoramic photograph (Oversize-folder 6)
      - 33rd NNIA (National Negro Insurance Association) convention, Miami, Florida, 1953 Sept. 22-24, panoramic photograph (Oversize-folder 7)
      - National Negro Insurance Association, silver anniversary convention, New York City, 1946 July 9-12, panoramic photograph (Oversize-folder 7)
        Group portrait of roughly 150 individuals.
      - National Insurance Association, 38th annual session, Columbus, Ohio, 1958 August 4-8, panoramic photograph (Oversize-folder 7)
      - NCM, Durham, N.C., home office force [AN.?] District Managers, 1931 January 29, panoramic photograph (Oversize-folder 7)
      - Untitled panoramic photograph, same location as print labeled "NCM home office force [AN.?] District Managers, 1931 January 29," undated (Oversize-folder 7)
        Banner in window of large building reads "Welcome NCM District Managers." Torn on left side, missing several inches from print. Same location as the print labeled January 29, 1931, "NCM Home office force [AN.?] District Managers," but features some of the same men; may be either the same year or a year before or after.
      - National Negro Insurance Association, silver anniversary convention, New York City, 1946, July 9-12, panoramic photograph (duplicate of previous print) (Oversize-folder 7)
        Label on back of print: "Contributed by the Greenville S.C. District, John Harper, District Sales Manager"
      - Western Underwriters Association, NC Mutual agents, Charlotte, N.C., 1924 April 24-25, panoramic photograph (Oversize-folder 7)
        Photograph taken by Carolina Studio, Charlotte, N.C.
      - 17th annual convention, National Negroes Insurance Association, Augusta, Georgia, 1937 May 26-28, panoramic photograph (Oversize-folder 7)
      - 19th annual convention of Kappa Alpha Psi fraternity, Durham, N.C., panoramic photograph by Ramsey Studio, 1929 December 27-31 (Oversize-folder 7)
      - Georgia state conference of NCM insurance agents, Augusta, Georgia, panoramic photograph by H. Stewart, Savannah, 1924 September 11-12 (Oversize-folder 7)
      - Untitled panoramic photograph of gathering of well-known African American leaders, including C.C. Spaulding, unknown location and event, before 1932 (Oversize-folder 7)
        Names listed on the back of the print include the following educational, legal, and religious leaders: John Hope; Julius Rosenwald (died 1932); Mary McLeod Bethune; [Dr. Harper] Councill Trenholm; W. [William] A.C. Hughes [prob. Jr.]; Ira D.A. Reed [?]; C.C. Spaulding; R.R. Morton; Channing Tobias; Chas. [Charles Harris] Wesley; Emmett [J.] Scott; Mordecai [Wyatt] Johnson; and W.R. [Books?]. There are also the words "Blueford A&T" and "Monroe [work?]." The first may refer to Ferdinand D. Bluford, president of A&T College in North Carolina (1925-1955).
      - NCM birthday celebration in honor of President C.C. Spaulding, [Durham, N.C.?], 1923 August 1, panoramic photograph (Oversize-folder 7)
      - 37th annual session of National Insurance Association fellowship luncheon, Hotel New Yorker, NYC, 1957 August 21, panoramic photograph (Oversize-folder 7)
      - NCM 3rd George Wayne Cox sales convention banquet, Hotel Prince George, unknown location, 1955 April 22, honoring George Wayne Cox, Vice President and Agency Director, panoramic photograph (Oversize-folder 7)
      - National Convention of Insurance Agents, Boston, Massachusetts, 1916 September 12, panoramic photograph, Panoramic photograph has adhered to its glass covering; handle carefully. (Oversize-folder 8)
        Taken in front of large downtown building; includes many women.
      - Giant panoramic photograph of NCM home office on Parrish Street, Durham, N.C., mounted on board, circa 1930s [digital version only]
        Digital version only of a very large (27x75 inches) photographic print mounted on board. Over time the board had severely deteriorated and had sustained damage in storage.
        Although a negative or smaller print of this image appears not to exist in the collection, there are oversize photographs of Durham, N.C. home office staff taken around or on the same date in the Photographic Materials, Historical Images subseries, or possibly in other locations in the Exhibit Materials Series.
        Please consult with Rubenstein Library staff for more assistance.
  - Slides, 1960-2005
    Contains slides stored separately from prints. Items are arranged in loose chronological order. Slides directly associated with prints are located in the Prints Subseries.
    - Asa Spaulding, circa 1960 (Box 134)
    - Events and people, 1989 (Box 134)
    - People and office, 2000-2005 (Box 134)
    - Events and people, 2004-2005 and undated (Box 186)
  - Items Closed Pending Conservation
    Fragile photographs, closed to use pending conservation treatment.
    - Twelve women on staff, Durham Office, mounted group portrait photograph, circa 1910 (Box 199)
    - Fragments from two mounted panoramic photos, early 1920s? (Box 199)
    - Prof. W. G. [William Gaston] Pearson (1885-1947), oval mounted photographic portrait,1920s (Oversize-box OV 53)
    - Large group shot, fragment of panorama, probably Durham Office, circa 1920 (Oversize-box OV 53)
    - Staff of Durham District Office, mounted group portrait, 1910 (Oversize-box OV 53)
    - Staff of Washington District Office (Newport News?), mounted group portrait, 1948 (Oversize-box OV 53)
    - Staff of Washington District Office (Newport News?), group portrait housed in cardboard portfolio with closure, circa 1948 (Oversize-box OV 53)
    - Men in front of building with sign, "Headquarters, National Negro Insurance Association," mounted panoramic photograph, Durham, 1920s? (Oversize-box OV 54)
    - Unidentified banquet in Chicago, panoramic photograph, circa 1950s (Oversize-box OV 54)
    - National Insurance Association (NIA) banquet, Philadelphia Sheraton, unmounted panorama, July 22, 1964 (Oversize-box OV 54)
    - Large photographic portrait of unidentified man, pastel or chalk overlay, 1910s? (Oversize-box OV 55)
      May be a member of the Spaulding family.
    - North Carolina Mutual District managers, in front of NC Mutual building, Parrish St., Durham, panoramic group photograph, after 1921 (Oversize-box OV 56)
- Printed Materials, 1903-2008 and undated; 1920s-1990s; 51 boxes
  Arranged into the following subseries: NCM Publications, Non-NCM Publications, and Periodical Clippings. The first two subseries are further subdivided into two large format groupings: Pamphlets and Other Publications, and Serials. These files were assembled by NCM staff and offer a rich array of printed resources on African American history, culture, and businesses. Formats include essays; reports; pamphlets; brochures and fliers for products, initiatives, and events; newsletters; newspapers and clippings; journals; popular serials; internal publications, including a full set of NC Mutual's serial, The Whetstone, promotional literature for North Carolina Mutual as well as other organizations, and a set of obituaries (1944-2005) memorializing company staff, most of which contain full biographies.